Sound Recordings of Museum-Related Events
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
- General Sound Recordings of Museum-Related Activities, 1939-present
  - "Eddie Palmieri and his Latin Jazz Orchestra", August 5, 1993, 9:00 PM; PERSONALITY: Geri Allen EXHIBITION: 1654.Latin American Artists of the Twentieth Century[MoMA Exh. #1654, June 2-September 7, 1993] DATA: 1 Standard Audio Cassette SUMMARY: Performance by Eddie Palmieri and his Latin Jazz Orchestra, introduced by Geri Allen. TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: January 2009; NOTE: This is an unofficial recording, provided by a source outside The Museum of Modern Art. (Item 2009.3)
  - "Root Expansions", July 15, 1993, 7:00 PM; PERSONALITY: Geri Allen EXHIBITION: 1654.Latin American Artists of the Twentieth Century[MoMA Exh. #1654, June 2-September 7, 1993] DATA: 1 Standard Audio Cassette SUMMARY: Performance by Craig Harris and others, introduced by Geri Allen. TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: January 2009; NOTE: This is an unofficial recording, provided by a source outside The Museum of Modern Art. (Item 2009.4)
  - "Joan Miro Scholars Day", November 11, 2008; PERSONALITY: Anne Umland EXHIBITION: Joan Miró: Painting and Anti-Painting 1927–1937, November 2, 2008–January 12, 2009 DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: Discussion and events for scholars surrounding Joan Miró: Painting and Anti-Painting 1927–1937, including a tour of the exhibition by curator Anne Umland. TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: February 2009 (Item 2009.5)
  - "Marlene Dumas: A Lecture with the Artist", December 08, 2008; PERSONALITY: Connie Butler EXHIBITION: Marlene Dumas: Measuring Your Own Grave, December 14, 2008 - February 16, 2009 DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: Marlene Dumas's paintings often focus on the human figure, merging existential human themes with personal experience and art historical antecedents. In this lecture, the artist presents her work and the upcoming exhibition Marlene Dumas: Measuring Your Own Grave just after the installation of the exhibition has been completed. TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: February 2009 (Item 2009.6)
  - "Joan Miro: New Approaches", November 11, 2008; PERSONALITY: Anne Umland EXHIBITION: Joan Miró: Painting and Anti-Painting 1927–1937, November 2, 2008–January 12, 2009 DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: To mark the close of the exhibition Joan Miró: Painting and Anti-Painting 1927–1937, MoMA hosts a daylong symposium to consider issues surrounding the artist's creative production during a transformative decade within his long career. A distinguished group of international scholars offer new approaches to this period of the artist's work, examining its relation to the crisis of painting in Surrealism, the specific nature of the French and Catalan avant-gardes of the time, and the broader sociopolitical situation that emerged in Europe as the 1920s came to an end and the political tensions that would lead to World War II became increasingly apparent. Participants include Dawn Ades, Professor of Art History and Theory at the University of Essex, and Co-Director of the Centre for Studies of Surrealism and its Legacies; Juan José Lahuerta, Professor, History of Art, Escola Técnica Superior d'Arquitectura, Barcelona; Susan Laxton, art historian (PhD, Columbia University); David Lomas, Reader in Art History, University of Manchester, England; Robert S. Lubar, Associate Professor, Institute of Fine Arts, New York University; Jordana Mendelson, Associate Professor, Spanish and Portuguese, New York University; and Charles Palermo, Associate Professor of Art History, Department of Art and Art History, The College of William and Mary. Anne Umland, Curator, Department of Painting and Sculpture, and organizer of the exhibition, introduces the day's presentations. The symposium closes with a roundtable discussion. TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: February 2009 (Item 2009.7)
  - "Open Source", January 20, 2009; SERIES: Artists Speak: Conversations on Contemporary Art with Glenn D. Lowry PARTICIPANTS: Moderator: Glenn Lowry, Director, The Museum of Modern Art; Cory Archangel; Rafael Lozano-Hemmer SPONSOR: Department of Education DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: This program explores contemporary art in the age of YouTube, Facebook, and Wikipedia, online resources that connect people and information in countless ways and through immeasurable distances. Artists Cory Arcangel and Rafael Lozano-Hemmer discuss the ways in which they utilize electronic databases to create works of art. Glenn D. Lowry, director of The Museum of Modern Art, moderates a discussion. RELATED MATERIAL: 2009-66 DONOR: Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: February 2009 (Item 2009.8)
  - "The Adventures of Krazy Kat", November 10, 2008; PLACE: The Celeste Bartos Theater SERIES: Modern Poets PARTICIPANTS: Monica Youn, poet; J. Hoberman, senior film critic, The Village Voice; Meghan O'Rourke, moderator. DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: In 1913, the cartoonist George Herriman created Krazy Kat, a comic strip that first appeared in William Randolph Hearst's New York Evening Journal. The cartoon was published in the United States until 1944, offering American and international readers constant companionship in its characters: Krazy Kat, an innocent cat of indeterminate gender; Ignatz Mouse, Krazy's antagonist; Offissa Pupp, the protective police dog; and others. This evening's program reconsiders Herriman's stories through the lens of comics and poetry. Poet Monica Youn reads her own collection of works about Ignatz, first published in The Paris Review in the summer of 2007; and J. Hoberman, senior film critic, The Village Voice, speaks about the impact of Krazy Kat on the comics medium. Meghan O'Rourke, poet, critic, and co–poetry editor, The Paris Review, moderates a discussion. This program is a collaboration between The Museum of Modern Art and The Paris Review. DONOR: The Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: February 2009 RELATED MATERIAL: 2009-5 (Item 2009.9)
  - "Mapping Nations", November 17, 2008; SERIES: Artists Speak: Conversations on Contemporary Art with Glenn D. Lowry PARTICIPANTS: Moderator: Glenn Lowry, Director, The Museum of Modern Art; Matt Coolidge; Miran Mohar; Borut Vogelnik SPONSOR: Department of Education DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: IRWIN is an artist collective based in Ljubljana, Slovenia, best known for their ongoing projects NSK State and East Art Map. NSK State is a utopian state without a concrete territory, questioning notions of borders and nationhood. East Art Map is a work focusing on retracing the contemporary art and history of Eastern Europe. The Center for Land Use Interpretation (CLUI) is a research organization that explores how the United States' lands are apportioned, utilized, and perceived. Matt Coolidge of CLUI and Miran Mohar and Borut Vogelnik of IRWIN discuss how they engage in the specific and symbolic meaning of territoriality and how they use the tools of art, research, and collaboration to present their projects both in and outside of museum contexts. Moderated by Glenn D. Lowry, director of The Museum of Modern Art. DONOR: Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: February 2009 RELATED MATERIAL: 2009-4, 2009-4D (Item 2009.10)
  - "Conversations with Contemporary Artists: Campaign Trails", October 30, 2008; SERIES: Conversations with Contemporary Artists PARTICIPANTS: Antoni Muntadas; Marshall Reese; Laura Flanders SPONSOR: Department of Education DATA: 2 CDs; TRT: 00:24:07 SUMMARY: With every presidential election beginning in 1984, Antoni Muntadas and Marshall Reese have compiled and edited Political Advertisement, a historical survey of television campaign spots from 1952 to the present. This anthology, updated to include advertisements from the 2008 presidential campaign, documents the selling of the American presidency since the 1950s. As Muntadas and Reese trace the development of the TV "spot," a social and media history emerges revealing how campaign spots have become a political strategy and manipulative marketing technique. This evening, the artists debut the latest version of Political Advertisement in a premiere presentation followed by commentary by Laura Flanders, journalist, Air America host of Radio Nation, and author of Blue Grit. DONOR: Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: February 2009 (Item 2009.11, 2009.11D)
  - "Two Wrenching Departures", September 28, 2006; SERIES: Video Premieres PLACE: The Museum of Modern Art, Titus Theater 1 PERSONALITY: Laurence Cardish PARTICIPANTS: Ken Jacobs, filmmaker. DATA: 1 CD; TRT: 00:32:14 SUMMARY: Ken Jacobs makes opening remarks and takes questions from the audience at the premiere screening of his film Two Wrenching Departures (2006). In October 1989, estranged friends Bob Fleischner and Jack Smith died within a week of each other. Ken Jacobs met Smith through Fleischner in 1955 at CUNY night school, where the three were studying camera techniques. This feature-length work, first performed in 1990 as a live Nervous System piece, was made in response to the loss of Jacobs’s friends. World premiere. DONOR: Department of Film TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: February 2009 (Item 2009.12)
  - "Conversations with Contemporary Artists: James Carpenter", April 7, 1995; SERIES: Conversations with Contemporary Artists PLACE: The Museum of Modern Art SERIES: Conversations with Contemporary Artists PARTICIPANTS: James Carpenter, artist. DATA: 1 Standard Audio Cassette SUMMARY: Artist James Carpenter lectures about his work. DONOR: Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: February 2009 (Item 2009.13)
  - "Francesc Torres on George Grosz", November 16, 1989; PLACE: The Museum of Modern Art PARTICIPANTS: Francesc Torres, artist. DATA: 1 Standard Audio Cassette SUMMARY: Artist Francesc Torres lectures about the influence of George Grosz in his work. TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: February 2009 (Item 2009.14)
  - "A Conversation about Norman Lewis", January 21, 1999; PLACE: The Museum of Modern Art PARTICIPANTS: Robert Storr, curator; Thelma Golden, curator; Jack Whitten, artist. DATA: 1 Standard Audio Cassette SUMMARY: Conversation between Thelma Golden and Jack Whitten about Norman Lewis, moderated by Robert Storr. DONOR: Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: February 2009 (Item 2009.15)
  - "Conversations with Contemporary Artists: Shigeru Ban", May 5, 2000; SERIES: Conversations with Contemporary Artists PLACE: The Museum of Modern Art PARTICIPANTS: Shigeru Ban, architect. DATA: 1 Standard Audio Cassette SUMMARY: Lecture by architect Shigeru Ban. DONOR: Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: February 2009 (Item 2009.16)
  - "A Screening of History of a Paper Tube Arch", June 13, 2000; PERSONALITY: Mathilda McQuaid, Associate Curator, Department of Architecture and Design EXHIBITION: Shigeru Ban: A Paper Arch [MoMA Exh. #1865, April 26(30)-August 1, 2000] PLACE: The Museum of Modern Art PARTICIPANTS: Judith Turner, filmmaker. DATA: 1 Standard Audio Cassette SUMMARY: Opening remarks by Mathilda Quaid, Associate Curator, Department of Architecture and Design, preceeding screening of film, History of a Paper Tube Arch (2000), as well as closing remarks by the director, Judith Turner. TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: February 2009 (Item 2009.17)
  - "Conversations with Contemporary Artists: The Family Edition: Jeffrey Scher", February 28, 2009; SERIES: Conversations with Contemporary Artists: The Family Edition PERSONALITY: Jeffrey Scher PLACE: The Museum of Modern Art, Celeste Bartos Theatre PARTICIPANTS: Cari Frisch, Family Programs Assistant; Jeffrey Scher, artist DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: Jeffrey Scher is fascinated by how the mind can create the illusion of movement from individual images. His hand-painted films are mosaics of color, light, and forms that rely on classic techniques. Children and adults are offered the opportunity to express their ideas about what they see in slide and video presentations given by artists, as well as to ask questions about art-making techniques and materials and artistic inspiration. DONOR: Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: March 2009 (Item 2009.18)
  - "After Hours with Ensor", July 15, 2009; PERSONALITY: Anna Swinbourne EXHIBITION:James Ensor DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: Anna Swinbourne, Assistant Curator, Department of Painting and Sculpture, and organizer of James Ensor, leads an after-hours discussion in the exhibition galleries. DONOR: Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: September 2009 (Item 2009.19)
  - "Conversations with Contemporary Artists: Teresa Margolles", July 9, 2009; SERIES: Conversations with Contemporary Artists PERSONALITY: Teresa Margolles PLACE: The Museum of Modern Art, Celeste Bartos Theatre DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: Teresa Margolles, one of the foremost artists working in Mexico today, is representing her country at this year’s Venice Biennale. In this program, presented in collaboration with the Mexican Cultural Institute of New York, Margolles discusses how she explores death, and the relics and rituals that surround it, with her installations, objects, and other media. The evening is moderated by Pablo Helguera, Director, Adult and Academic Programs, The Museum of Modern Art. RELATED MATERIAL: 2009-54 DONOR: Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: September 2009 (Item 2009.20)
  - "Raw Edges", July 24, 2009; SERIES: Modern Poets EXHIBITION:Looking at Music: Side Two PARTICIPANTS: Richard Hell, Eileen Myles, Saul Williams DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: This reading features poetry that was influenced by the experimental music and media scene of the 1970s, and which responded to the era’s urban blight and depressed economies. Participants include musician and writer Richard Hell, poet Eileen Myles, and poet, actor, and musician Saul Williams. DONOR: The Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: September 2009 (Item 2009.21)
  - "5 x 20 x 20", May 4, 2009; EXHIBITION:Compass in Hand: Selections from The Judith Rothschild Foundation Contemporary Drawings Collection PLACE: The Celeste Bartos Theater, The Museum of Modern Art PARTICIPANTS: Ester Partegàs, Tom Knechtel, Amy Cutler, Jeff Davis, Jaime Davidovich DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: This is first event in a series of talks in the format of Pecha Kucha, an informal Japanese lecture style, that celebrates a gift by The Judith Rothschild Foundation to MoMA of works by over 650 artists. In each session, approximately five artists who are represented in the collection discuss twenty slides of their work, twenty seconds per slide. RELATED MATERIAL: 2009.23, 2009.24, 2009.25, 2009.26, 2009.27, 2009-40, 2009-41, 2009-42, 2009-43, 2009-44, 2009-45 DONOR: The Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: September 2009 (Item 2009.22)
  - "5 x 20 x 20", May 7, 2009; EXHIBITION:Compass in Hand: Selections from The Judith Rothschild Foundation Contemporary Drawings Collection PLACE: The Celeste Bartos Theater, The Museum of Modern Art PARTICIPANTS: Christian Holstad, Julian Hoeber, Dannielle Tegeder, Elizabeth Simonson, Kim Jones, Dana Schutz DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: This is second event in a series of talks in the format of Pecha Kucha, an informal Japanese lecture style, that celebrates a gift by The Judith Rothschild Foundation to MoMA of works by over 650 artists. In each session, approximately five artists who are represented in the collection discuss twenty slides of their work, twenty seconds per slide. RELATED MATERIAL: 2009.22, 2009.24, 2009.25, 2009.26, 2009.27, 2009-40, 2009-41, 2009-42, 2009-43, 2009-44, 2009-45 DONOR: The Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: September 2009 (Item 2009.23)
  - "5 x 20 x 20", May 11, 2009; EXHIBITION:Compass in Hand: Selections from The Judith Rothschild Foundation Contemporary Drawings Collection PLACE: The Celeste Bartos Theater, The Museum of Modern Art PARTICIPANTS: Aaron Johnson, Marlene McCarty, Michael Scoggins, Renato Orara, Chloe Piene DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: This is the third event in a series of talks in the format of Pecha Kucha, an informal Japanese lecture style, that celebrates a gift by The Judith Rothschild Foundation to MoMA of works by over 650 artists. In each session, approximately five artists who are represented in the collection discuss twenty slides of their work, twenty seconds per slide. RELATED MATERIAL: 2009.22, 2009.23, 2009.25, 2009.26, 2009.27, 2009-40, 2009-41, 2009-42, 2009-43, 2009-44, 2009-45 DONOR: The Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: September 2009 (Item 2009.24)
  - "5 x 20 x 20", May 14, 2009; EXHIBITION:Compass in Hand: Selections from The Judith Rothschild Foundation Contemporary Drawings Collection PLACE: The Celeste Bartos Theater, The Museum of Modern Art PARTICIPANTS: Katerina Lanfranco, Marcia Hafif, David Opdyke, Yuri Masnyj, Robert Buck, Michael Rodriguez DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: This is the fourth event in a series of talks in the format of Pecha Kucha, an informal Japanese lecture style, that celebrates a gift by The Judith Rothschild Foundation to MoMA of works by over 650 artists. In each session, approximately five artists who are represented in the collection discuss twenty slides of their work, twenty seconds per slide. RELATED MATERIAL: 2009.22, 2009.23, 2009.24, 2009.26, 2009.27, 2009-40, 2009-41, 2009-42, 2009-43, 2009-44, 2009-45 DONOR: The Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: September 2009 (Item 2009.25)
  - "5 x 20 x 20", May 18, 2009; EXHIBITION:Compass in Hand: Selections from The Judith Rothschild Foundation Contemporary Drawings Collection PLACE: The Celeste Bartos Theater, The Museum of Modern Art PARTICIPANTS: Kurt Kauper, Tamara Gayer, Rachel Selekman, Dave Muller, Gerry Hayes, Randall Sellers DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: This is the fifth event in a series of talks in the format of Pecha Kucha, an informal Japanese lecture style, that celebrates a gift by The Judith Rothschild Foundation to MoMA of works by over 650 artists. In each session, approximately five artists who are represented in the collection discuss twenty slides of their work, twenty seconds per slide. RELATED MATERIAL: 2009.22, 2009.23, 2009.24, 2009.25, 2009.27, 2009-40, 2009-41, 2009-42, 2009-43, 2009-44, 2009-45 DONOR: The Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: September 2009 (Item 2009.26)
  - "5 x 20 x 20", May 21, 2009; EXHIBITION:Compass in Hand: Selections from The Judith Rothschild Foundation Contemporary Drawings Collection PLACE: The Celeste Bartos Theater, The Museum of Modern Art PARTICIPANTS: Jonathan Horowitz, James Siena, Joan Banach, Simone Shubuck, Stephen Sollins DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: This is the sixth and final event in a series of talks in the format of Pecha Kucha, an informal Japanese lecture style, that celebrates a gift by The Judith Rothschild Foundation to MoMA of works by over 650 artists. In each session, approximately five artists who are represented in the collection discuss twenty slides of their work, twenty seconds per slide. RELATED MATERIAL: 2009.22, 2009.23, 2009.24, 2009.25, 2009.26, 2009-40, 2009-41, 2009-42, 2009-43, 2009-44, 2009-45 DONOR: The Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: September 2009 (Item 2009.27)
  - "Knowing Kippenberger", April 14, 2009; EXHIBITION:Martin Kippenberger: The Problem Perspective[MoMA Exh. #2068, March 1-May 11, 2009] PLACE: The Roy and Niuta Titus Theater 2, The Museum of Modern Art PARTICIPANTS: Rachel Harrison, Jeff Koons, Friedrich Petzel, Jan Avgikos DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: Martin Kippenberger's The Happy End of Franz Kafka's "Amerika" stages the scenario of America as the land of the job interview. In the spirit of this work, tonight's program takes the shape of a series of interviews between artists, art dealers, and friends of Kippenberger's. Together they help to form a collective portrait of this complicated figure. Participants include artists Rachel Harrison and Jeff Koons, art dealer Friedrich Petzel, and critic and art historian Jan Avgikos. RELATED MATERIAL: 2009-53 DONOR: The Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: September 2009 (Item 2009.28)
  - "An Evening with Aernout Mik", May 11, 2009; EXHIBITION:Aernout Mik[MoMA Exh. #2078, May 6-July 27, 2009] PLACE: The Roy and Niuta Titus Theater 2, The Museum of Modern Art SERIES: Modern Mondays PARTICIPANTS: Aernout Mik, artist/filmmaker; Lawrence Kardish; Glenn D. Lowry DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: On the occasion of the MoMA exhibition Aernout Mik, the first U.S. museum survey of the artist's work, Modern Mondays presents a virtual tour of the eight works spread throughout the Museum. Mik designs, sculpts, and builds constructions that both contain his moving images and engage the body of the spectator, creating a kinesthetic relationship between viewer and viewed. These moving-image installations uniquely meld filmmaking, sculpture, and architecture into an experience that is at once compelling, unsettling, and original. Following a presentation by Laurence Kardish, organizer of the exhibition, Mik participates in a conversation with MoMA Director Glenn Lowry. DONOR: The Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: September 2009 (Item 2009.29)
  - "Transpedagogy: Contemporary Art and the Vehicles of Education", May 15, 2009; PLACE: The Celeste Bartos Theater, The Museum of Modern Art SERIES: Contemporary Art Forum PARTICIPANTS: Mark Allen, Director of the non-profit performance/installation space Machine Project; Claire Bishop, Associate Professor of Art History at the Graduate Center, New York; Tania Bruguera, artist; Jessica Gogan, Assistant Director for Education and Interpretation, The Andy Warhol Museum, Pittsburgh; Grant Kester, Associate Professor, Art History Visual Arts Department, University of California, San Diego; Adam Lerner, Director of the Museum of Contemporary Art, Denver, and Chief Animator in the Department of Structures and Fictions; Bernardo Ortiz, artist and member of Lugar a Dudas, Cali, Colombia; Sally Tallant, Head of Education and Public Programmes at the Serpentine Gallery, London; Phillip Van den Bossche, Director, Kunstmuseum Aan Zee, Oostende, Belgium; artist Qiu Zhijie DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: What role has art education played in contemporary art practice? Artists, scholars, and critics talk about collaborative and participatory art, pedagogical experiments, and how such art can be understood and discussed. This two-part symposium is presented in collaboration with The Serpentine Gallery, London. RELATED MATERIAL: Please see Transcripts, Folder 120; 2009-48a, 2009-48b, 2009-48c DONOR: The Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: September 2009 (Item 2009.30)
  - "Who's a Filmmaker? Cinema Beyond a Darkened Room", May 6, 2009; PLACE: The Celeste Bartos Theater, The Museum of Modern Art PARTICIPANTS: Donna De Salvo; Eleanor Heartney; Amy Taubin; Laurence Kardish DATA: 1 CD SUMMARY: This program examines the fluidity of boundaries in film. Art and film critics and museum curators address the idea of cinema in the art world, where attitudes toward the moving image seem to differ from those toward "movies." Donna De Salvo, Chief Curator and Associate Director for Programs, Whitney Museum of American Art, explores the problem of categorization as it relates to cinema in the galleries, or, where art meets the museum. Eleanor Heartney, contributing editor to Art in America and Artpress, addresses how artists borrow and manipulate actual cinematic works for different ends and how they use and subvert cinematic techniques, and Amy Taubin, film critic, discusses the construction of the temporal and social experiences in both a traditional cinematic environment and in art installations. Laurence Kardish, Senior Curator, Department of Film, and organizer of the exhibition, moderates a conversation. DONOR: The Department of Education TRANSFERRED TO ARCHIVES: September 2009 (Item 2009.31)